Guide to the United Methodist Church Records, 1784-1984, bulk 1800-1940
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- N.C. Conference Records Series, 1784-1974, bulk 1838-1939
  - Conference Records Subseries (Restricted), 1812-1953, bulk 1838-1931
    - Journals
      - Originals
        - 1894-1897(F-2733) (Box NCC15)
        - 1898-1901(F-2734) (Box NCC16)
        - 1902-1905(F-2735) (Box NCC17)
        - 1906-1909(F-2736) (Box NCC18)
        - 1910-1913(F-2737) (Box NCC19)
    - Methodist boys in military service, lists and correspondence compiled by M. T. Plyler, 1918 Oct.-Dec. (Box NCC20)
    - Raleigh Advocate Publishing Co.
      - Raleigh Christian Advocate financial papers and correspondence, 1879-1894 and undated
      - Minute Book, 1902-1919(M-6910)
    - Relief Society minutes, 1838-1847(M-2723)
      An organization that gave financial aid to ministers, their widows, and children.
    - Receipts and other material (MEC, MECS, MC), 1812-1953 and undated
    - Sunday School Board minutes and reports, 1926-1931, (3 folders)
    - Trials of Ministers
      - MECS vs J. T. Abernathy, 1891, (3 folders)
      - MECS vs J. T. Bagwell, 1886, (2 folders) (Box NCC21)
      - Appeal of D. D. Bailey, 1888, 1893
      - MECS vs J. B. Bobbitt, 1888, (6 folders)
      - MECS vs D. R. Bruton, 1890
      - MECS vs W. A. Forbes, 1893
      - MECS vs L. L. Hendren, 1885
      - MECS vs R. J. Moorman, 1901
      - MECS vs G. A. Oglesby, 1890
  - District Records Subseries, 1866-1939
    Comprises bound volumes of District Conference Minutes and Quarterly Conference Minutes that document the administrative activities of districts within the N.C. Conference. There may be some overlap with the Western N.C. Conference. Districts with the largest number of records include Durham (1885-1927), Elizabeth City (1911-1922), Raleigh (1914-1915 and 1935-1939), and Wilmington (1866-1898). The Elizabeth City District also includes reports from various circuits (1894-1910). Some districts were originally part of either the Va. or S.C. Conferences, and this is noted next to their name.
    Arranged alphabetically by district name. Within each district name is included a list of counties represented in the district, as well as a list of the circuits, charges, and churches in this collection that were in that district. Names of districts represented in the Circuit, Charge, and Church Records Subseries but for which there no district-level records are also listed in this subseries. Date ranges in this series are given for district-level records only. Oversize items have been removed to the Oversize Materials section of this finding aid.
    - [Burlington District: No district records] (Box NCC22)
      Counties represented in the Burlington District: Alamance.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Burlington District: Mt. Hermon Circuit.
    - [Catawba District, N.C. and S.C. Conferences: No district records] (Box NCC22)
      Counties represented in the Catawba District: Lincoln.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Catawba District: Lincolnton Circuit.
    - [Charlotte District, N.C. and Western N.C. Conferences: No district records] (Box NCC22)
      Counties represented in the Charlotte District: Anson, and Union.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Charlotte District: Ansonville Circuit; and Monroe, Matthews and Clear Creek Circuits.
    - [Danville District, N.C. and Va. Conferences: No district records] (Box NCC22)
      Counties represented in the Danville District: Caswell, Chatham, and Randolph.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Danville District: Caswell Circuit; Cedar Falls Station and Franklinsville; Chatham Circuit; Franklinsville Circuit; and Yanceyville Circuit.
    - Durham District, 1885-1923, 1926-1927 (Box NCC22)
      Counties represented in the Durham District: Alamance, Caswell, Chatham, Durham, and Person.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Durham District: Burlington Charge/Station; Burlington, Graham, and Haw River Charge; Carr Church; Duke Memorial Church; Durham Circuit; Front Street Charge/Church; Gregson Street Church; Haw River Circuit; Leasburg Circuit; Main Street Church; Milton Circuit/Charge; Pittsboro Circuit/Church/Charge; Woodsdale Circuit/Charge; and Yanceyville Circuit.
      - District Conference Minutes
        - 1885-1895(F-2749)
          Includes Hillsboro District, 1882-1884.
        - 1896-1912(F-2750)
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes
        - 1912-1913(F-2710)
        - 1914-1915(F-2713)
        - 1915-1916(M-2714)
        - 1916-1917(M-2715) (Box NCC23)
        - 1917-1918(M-2716)
        - 1918-1919(M-2717)
        - 1920-1921(M-2718)
        - 1922-1923(M-2719)
        - 1926-1927(M-4291)
    - Elizabeth City District, 1894-1914, 1919-1922 (Box NCC24)
      Counties represented in the Elizabeth City District: Beaufort, Camden, Chowan, Currituck, Dare, Gates, Pasquotank, Perquimans, Tyrrel, and Unknown.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Elizabeth City District: Bethany Church; Camden Circuit; Chowan Circuit; Columbia Circuit; Dare Circuit; Elizabeth City Station; Gates Circuit; Hatteras Circuit; Hertford Church; Hertford Circuit; Kitrell's Church; Kitty Hawk Charge; Kitty Hawk Circuit; Moyock Circuit; North Gates Circuit; Pantego Circuit/Charge; Pasquotank Circuit; Perquimans Circuit; Roanoke Island Circuit/Station; and South Camden Circuit.
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes
        - 1911-1912(M-2708)
        - 1912-1913(M-2709)
        - 1913-1914(M-2711)
        - 1919(M-2746)
        - 1919-1920(M-2821)
        - 1921(M-2747)
        - 1921-1922(M-2822)
      - Reports from Various Circuits, 1894-1910 (Box NCC25)
    - Fayetteville District, 1922-1923 (Box NCC25)
      Counties represented in the Fayetteville District: Alamance, Bladen, Brunswick, Chatham, Montgomery, Richmond, and Wake.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Fayetteville District: Buckhorn and Cokesbury Churches; Buckhorn Circuit; Cape Fear Circuit; Elizabeth Circuit/Charge; Haw River Circuit; Montgomery Circuit; Pittsboro Circuit/Church/Charge; and Rockingham Circuit.
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1922-1923(M-2863)
    - [Greensboro District: No district records. See also the Western N.C. Conference.] (Box NCC25)
      Counties represented in the Greensboro District: Alamance, Caswell, Chatham, Forsyth, Guilford, Montgomery, Randolph, and Stokes.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Greensboro District: Cedar Falls Station and Franklinsville; Chatham Circuit; Forsyth Circuit; Franklinsville Circuit; Guilford Circuit; Haw River Circuit; Montgomery Circuit; Pleasant Garden Circuit; Randolph Circuit; South Guilford Circuit; Stokes Circuit; Trinity College Circuit; and Yanceyville Circuit.
    - Hillsboro District, 1882-1884 (Box NCC25)
      Counties represented in the Hillsboro District: Alamance, Caswell, Chatham, Guilford, and Randolph.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Hillsboro District: Cedar Falls Station and Franklinsville; Chatham Circuit; Franklinsville Circuit; Guilford Mission; Haw River Circuit; Leasburg Circuit; South Guilford and Pleasant Garden Circuits; and Yanceyville Circuit.
      - [District Conference Minutes, 1882-1884: Found in Durham District, District Conference Minutes, 1885-1896.]
    - [Lincolnton District, N.C. and Va. Conferences: No district records. See also the Western N.C. Conference.] (Box NCC25)
      Counties represented in the Lincolnton District: Lincoln.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Lincolnton District: Lincolnton Circuit.
    - [Murfreesboro District, N.C. and Va. Conferences: No district records] (Box NCC25)
      Counties represented in the Murfreesboro District: Camden, Chowan, Currituck, Dare, Gates, Hertford, Pasquotank, and Perquimans.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Murfreesboro District: Bertie Circuit; Camden Circuit; Currituck Mission; Dare Circuit; Dare Mission; Gates Circuit; Gates and Bertie Circuit; Gates and Edenton Circuit; Hertford Circuit; Kitty Hawk Mission; Murfreesboro amd Gates Circuit; North Gates Circuit; Pasquotank Circuit; and Roanoke Island Circuit/Station.
    - New Bern District, 1893-1909 (Box NCC25)
      Counties represented in the New Bern District: Carteret and Craven.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the New Bern District: Newport and Trent Circuits.
      - District Conference Records, 1893-1909(F-2879)
    - [Norfolk District, N.C. and Va. Conferences: No district records] (Box NCC25)
      Counties represented in the Norfolk District: Camden, Chowan, Currituck, Dare, Gates, Hertford, and Pasquotank.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Norfolk District: Bertie Circuit; Currituck Circuit; Currituck Mission; Dare Mission; Gates Circuit; Gates and Edenton Circuit; Murfreesboro and Gates Circuit; and Pasquotank Circuit.
    - [Norfolk and Murfreesboro District: No district records. See either the Norfolk or the Murfreesboro Districts.] (Box NCC25)
    - Raleigh District, 1914-1915, 1935-1939 (Box NCC25)
      Counties represented in the Raleigh District: Alamance, Chatham, Randolph, Wake, and Warren.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Durham District: Buckhorn and Cokesbury Churches; Buckhorn Circuit; Cary Circuit; Cedar Falls Station and Franklinsville; Chatham Circuit; Franklinsville Circuit; Haw River Circuit; and Henderson Station.
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes/Records
        - 1914-1915(M-2712)
        - 1935-1936(M-4296)
        - 1936-1937(M-4297)
        - 1937-1938(M-4298) (Box NCC26)
        - 1938-1939(M-4299)
    - Rockingham District, 1913-1914 (Box NCC26)
      Counties represented in the Rockingham District: Bladen.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Rockingham District: Elizabeth Circuit/Charge.
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes/Minutes of Presiding Elder
        - 1913-1914(M-2883)
    - Salisbury District, N.C. and Va. Conferences, 1868-1875 (See also the Western N.C. Conference.) (Box NCC26)
      Counties represented in the Salisbury District: Forsyth, and Iredell.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Salisbury District: Forsyth Circuit; and Iredell Circuit.
      - District Conference Minutes, 1868-1875(L-2884)
    - Shelby District, N.C. and S.C. Conferences, 1870-1876 (See also the Western N.C. Conference.) (Box NCC27)
      Counties represented in the Shelby District: Burke, Cleveland, Gaston, and Lincoln.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Durham District: Double Shoals Circuit; Gaston Circuit; Lincolnton Circuit; Lincolnton Station; Morganton Circuit; Rock Spring Circuit; and Stanley Creek Circuit.
      - District Conference Minutes
        - 1870-1874
          Includes minutes from 1867-1870, when district was in the S.C. Conference.
        - 1875-1876 and undated
    - [Spartanburg District, N.C. and S.C. Conferences: No district records] (Box NCC27)
      Counties represented in the Spartanburg District: Lincoln.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Spartanburg District: Lincolnton Circuit.
    - [Suffolk District, N.C. and Va. Conferences: No district records] (Box NCC27)
      Counties represented in the Suffolk District: Camden, Gates, Pasquotank, and Perquimans.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Suffolk District: Camden Circuit; Gates Circuit; Hertford Circuit; North Gates Charge; Noth Gates Circuit; Pasquotank Circuit; and Perquimans Circuit.
    - Trinity College District, 1885-1890 (Box NCC27)
      Counties represented in the Trinity College District: Chatham, Guilford, and Randolph.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Trinity College District: Cedar Falls Station and Franklinsville; Chatham Circuit; Franklinsville Circuit; Randolph Circuit; South Guilford and Pleasant Garden Circuits; and Trinity College Circuit.
      - District Conference Minutes, 1885-1890(M-4290)
    - Warrenton District, 1913-1915 (Box NCC27)
      Counties represented in the Warrenton District: Halifax, and Warren.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Warrenton District: Roanoke Circuit.
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes
        - 1913-1914(M-2882)
        - 1914-1915(M-2881)
    - Washington District, 1896-1910 (Box NCC27)
      Counties represented in the Washington District: Beaufort, Dare, Pamlico, Tyrrel, Warren, and [Unknown].
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Washington District: Bath Circuit; Columbia Circuit; Dare Circiut; First Methodist Church; Hatteras Circuit; Ocracoke and Hatteras Circuit; Roanoke Island Circuit/Station; and Washington Station.
      - District Conference Minutes, 1896-1910(F-2905)
      - Quarterly Conference Minutes/Minutes of Presiding Elder (Box NCC28)
        - 1907(M-2906)
        - 1907-1908(M-2907)
    - Wilmington District, 1866-1898 (Box NCC28)
      Counties represented in the Wilmington District: Bladen, Dare, and New Hanover.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Wilmington District: Elizabeth Circuit/Charge; Fifth Street Charge/Church/Station; and Kitty Hawk Mission.
      - [District Conference Records, 1866-1898 (F-2908): Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS1.]
        Includes references to the need for public education. Minutes beginning in 1897 are housed in the Methodist Archives in Raleigh.
    - Wilson District, District records only, 1892-1894 (Box NCC28)
      - [District Conference Minutes, 1892-1894 (F-2926): Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS2.]
    - [Yadkin District, N.C. and Va. Conferences: No district records] (Box NCC28)
      Counties represented in the Yadkin District: Iredell.
      Circuits, charges, and/or churches in this collection that were in the Yadkin District: Iredell Circuit.
  - Circuit, Charge, and Church Records Subseries, 1784-1974, bulk 1841-1919
    Comprises primarily bound volumes of quarterly conference minutes that document the administrative life of Methodist Episcopal Church, South (MECS) circuits, charges, churches, missions, and stations in the eastern and central counties of North Carolina, especially those that until the late 1800s were part of the Virginia Conference. Counties with the most records in this subseries include Bladen, Caswell, Chatham, Dare (also Va.), Durham, Gates (also Va.), New Hanover, Perquimans (also Va.), and Wake. There is some overlap with the Western N.C. Conference. Records that span a large number of years and comprise a complete set of minutes during those years include Bath Circuit (Beaufort Co., 1849-1894), Dare Circuit (Dare Co., 1859-1903), Fifth Street Charge/Church/Station (New Hanover Co., 1844-1905), Gates Circuit (Gates Co., 1784-1911), Iredell Circuit (Iredell Co., 1823-1873), Leasburg Circuit (Caswell Co., 1883-1930), North Gates Circuit (Gates Co., 1884-1937), Pasquotank Circuit (Pasquotank Co., 1852-1906), Pittsboro Circuit (Chatham Co., 1854-1943), and Yanceyville Circuit (Caswell Co., 1844-1902).
    Some of the oldest records, from 1784 to about 1851, include Bath Circuit (Beaufort Co., 1849-1891); Bertie Circuit (Gates Co., 1817-1822); Burlington, Graham, and Haw River Charge (Alamance Co., 1849-1852); Chatham Circuit (Chatham Co., 1833-1841); Currituck Circuit (Currituck Co., 1829-1838); Fifth Street Charge/Church/Station (New Hanover Co., 1844-1851); Gates Circuit (Gates Co., 1784-1840); Guilford Circuit (Guilford Co., 1832-1865); Iredell Circuit (Iredell Co., 1823-1873); Lincolton Circuit (Lincoln Co., 1828-1876); Newport and Trent Circuits (Carteret and Craven Cos., 1837-1844); and Yanceyville Circuit (Caswell Co., 1844-1877).
    Some of the latest records, from 1930 to 1974, include Elizabeth Circuit (1875-1974), Duke Memorial Church (Durham Co., 1885-1970), North Gates Circuit (Gates Co., 1884-1937), Leasburg Circuit (Caswell Co., 1883-1930), and Pittsboro Circuit (Chatham Co., 1854-1943).
    In addition to the quarterly conference minutes, there are also education, financial, missionary contribution, ministers, Sunday school, Epworth League, and Women's Missionary Society reports and minutes (Buckhorn Circuit, Wake Co.; Duke Memorial Church and Main Street Church, Durham Co.); membership, Sunday school, abstinence society, and class lists (Buckhorn Circuit, Wake Co.; Currituck Circuit, Currituck Co.; Forsyth Circuit, Forsyth Co.); plans of circuits (Currituck Circuit, Currituck Co.; Forsyth Circuit, Forsyth Co.); and notes, drawings, and inventories of church buildings and furniture (Iredell Circuit, Iredell Co.; Roanoke Circuit, Halifax Co.). The Buckhorn and Cokesbury Churches records (Haw River Circuit, Wake Co.) include subscription lists to support the gospel on Haw River and Buckhorn Circuits, 1855-1858.
    Arranged by county (boundaries current in 2004) and then alphabetically by circuit, charge, church, mission, or station name. Records from counties in the western section of North Carolina can be found in the Western N.C. Conference Series. Additional information on circuits, charges, churches, missions, and stations may be found in the N.C. Conference Series, District Records Subseries, as well as the Historical Sketches Series, Circuits/Counties Subseries and the Churches/Cities Subseries. Information about ministers and other Methodists can be found alphabetically by last name in the Historical Sketches Series, Ministers Subseries, while overviews of Methodism in general, and in North Carolina and Virginia in specific, can be found in the Historical Sketches Series, Methodism Subseries. Oversize items have been removed to the Oversize Materials section of this finding aid. All circuit, charge, church, mission, and station names listed in this subseries can also be found alphabetically arranged without regard for their county, district, or conference location in the Circuit, Charge, and Station Index and the Church and Mission Index at the end of this finding aid. Baptismal records found in this collection can be located through the Baptismal Records Index.
    - Alamance Co., 1841-1868, 1895-1906 (See also the Western N.C. Conference.)
      - [Buckhorn Circuit, multiple districts: see Wake Co., Buckhorn Circuit.] (Box NCC29)
        - [Buckhorn Church: see Wake Co., Buckhorn Circuit, Buckhorn Church.
        - [Cokesbury Church: see Wake Co., Buckhorn Circuit, Cokesbury Church.]
      - Burlington Charge/Station, Durham District, 1897-1900, 1903-1906 (See also Durham Co., Front Street Church.)
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes
          - 1897-1900(M-2753)
            Includes Burlington, Graham, and Haw River Charge, 1897-1898; and Front Street Charge, 1900.
          - 1903-1906(M-2756)
      - [Burlington, Graham, and Haw River Charge, Durham District, 1897-1898: Found in Alamance Co., Burlington Charge, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1897-1900.]
      - Haw River Circuit, multiple districts, 1841-1852, 1854-1887
        1842-1851?: Circuit in Raleigh or in Greensboro Districts
        1850?-1866: Circuit in Fayetteville or in Greensboro Districts
        1866-1868: Circuit in Greensboro District
        At least 1881: Circuit in Hillsboro District
        At least 1878: Circuit in Durham District
        - [Buckhorn Church: See Wake Co., Buckhorn Circuit, Buckhorn Church.]
        - Church Book, 1841-1852(M-6170)
        - [Cokesbury Church: See Wake Co., Buckhorn Circuit, Cokesbury Church.]
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1854-1887(F-2864)
          Includes Pittsboro Circuit, 1868-1887.
      - Mt. Hermon Circuit, Burlington District, Class Book, 1895-1898 (F-5916)
      - [Pittsboro Circuit, Durham District: See Chatham Co., Pittsboro Circuit.]
    - Anson Co., 1860-1881
      - Ansonville Circuit, Charlotte District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1860-1881 (L-2745) (Box NCC30)
    - Beaufort Co., 1849-1902
      - Bath Circuit, Washington District, 1849-1902 (Box NCC30)
        - [Church Records, 1860-1902 (F-2892): Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS3.]
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes
          - 1849-1891(F-2895)
          - 1891-1894(M-2893)
      - Pantego Circuit/Charge, Elizabeth City District, Quarterly Conference Minutes 1896-1898 (M-2847 and one folder)
    - Bladen Co., 1875-1933, 1945-1974
      - Elizabeth Circuit/Charge, mulitple districts, 1875-1933, 1945-1974 (Box NCC30)
        1875-1903: Circuit in Wilmington District
        1905-1921: Circuit in Rockingham District
        1922-1933: Circuit in Fayetteville District
        1933?-1949 (1945-1949 certain): Circuit in Wilmington District
        - Church Register
          - No. 1, 1888-1903 (Also available in microfilm.)
          - [No. 2, 1898-1930: Removed to Oversize Materials, Box OS3. Also available in microfilm.]
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes
          - 1875-1887(M-2913)
          - 1887-1891(M-2918)
          - 1892-1895(M-2914)
          - 1896-1899(M-2915) (Box NCC31)
          - 1900-1903(M-2916)
          - 1904-1907(M-2917)
          - 1908-1949 (Also available on microfilm.), (1-7 of 8 volumes or folders)
          - 1908-1949 (Also available on microfilm.), (8 of 8 volumes or folders) (Box NCC32)
        - Singletary Church
          - Church Register, 1883-1974 (bulk 1900-1952)
          - Quarterly Conference Minutes
            - 1895-1905(M-4293)
            - 1905-1920(M-4294)
    - Brunswick Co., 1865-1870
      - Cape Fear Circuit, Fayetteville District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1865-1870 (Box NCC32)
    - Burke Co., 1857-1872
      - Morganton Circuit, Shelby District, 1857-1872 (Box NCC32)
        - Brindletown Church Class Book, 1857-1872(S-96)
    - Camden Co., 1877-1909
      - Camden Circuit, multiple districts, 1877-1909 (Box NCC32)
        At least 1877-1885: Circuit in Murfreesboro District, Va. Conference
        At least 1890: Circuit in Murfreesboro District, Va. Conference
        1891-1893: Circuit in Suffolk District, Va. Conference
        Until 1895: Circuit in Va. Conference; moved to N.C. Conference
        1895-1897: Circuit in Elizabeth City District, N.C. Conference
        - Quarterly Conference Minutes/Records
          - 1877-1885
          - 1886-1889(M-2931)
          - 1890(M-2932)
          - 1891-1893(M-2932)
          - 1893-1897(M-2933)
          - 1898-1901(M-2818) (Box NCC33)
          - 1901-1905(M-2819)
          - 1905-1909(M-2820)
      - [Pasquotank Circuit, multiple districts: See Pasquotank Co., Pasquotank Circuit.]
      - South Camden Circuit, Elizabeth City District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1899-1902 (M-2862)
    - Carteret and Craven Cos., 1837-1844
      - Newport and Trent Circuits, New Bern District, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1837-1844 (M-2928) (Box NCC33)
    - Caswell Co., 1844-1877, 1883-1930
      - [Caswell Circuit, Danville District, 1844-1854: Found in Caswell Co., Yanceyville Circuit, Quarterly Conference Minutes, 1844-1877.] (Box NCC33)
      - Leasburg Circuit, multiple districts, 1883-1930
        Until 1885: Circuit in Hillsboro District
        After 1885: Circuit in Durham District
        - Bethany Church, Church Conference Minutes, 1884-1902(M-2748)
          Includes Leasburg Church, 1883-1902.